<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Twelve arguments drawn out of the Scripture, wherein the commonly received opinion touching the deity of the Holy Spirit, is clearly and fully refuted. To which is prefixed a letter tending to the same purpose, written to a Member of the Honourable House of Commons. And to which is subjoyned an exposition of five principall passages of the Scripture, alleadged by the adversaries to prove the deity of the Holy Spirit; together with an answer to their grand objection touching the supposed omnipresence of the Holy Spirit. / By Iohn Bidle, Master of Arts.</title>
            <author>Biddle, John, 1615-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76702</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B2879</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E406_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201902</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862386</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862386</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114544</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76702)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114544)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 64:E406[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Twelve arguments drawn out of the Scripture, wherein the commonly received opinion touching the deity of the Holy Spirit, is clearly and fully refuted. To which is prefixed a letter tending to the same purpose, written to a Member of the Honourable House of Commons. And to which is subjoyned an exposition of five principall passages of the Scripture, alleadged by the adversaries to prove the deity of the Holy Spirit; together with an answer to their grand objection touching the supposed omnipresence of the Holy Spirit. / By Iohn Bidle, Master of Arts.</title>
                  <author>Biddle, John, 1615-1662.</author>
                  <author>I. H.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare 1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>"To the impartiall reader" is signed: I.H.</note>
                  <note>"This book was burnt by order of Parliament, 8 Sept."--Thomason Catalogue. McAlpin Catalogue has September 7.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Septemb. 6th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Holy Spirit --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Trinity --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114544:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:114544:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Twelve ARGVMENTS Drawn out of the Scripture, Wherein the commonly received Opinion touching the Deity of the Holy Spirit, is clearly and fully refuted.</p>
            <p>To which is prefixed a <hi>Letter</hi> tending to the ſame purpoſe, written to a Member of the Honourable Houſe of Commons.</p>
            <p>And to which is ſubjoyned an <hi>Expoſition</hi> of five prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall Paſſages of the Scripture, alleadged by the Adverſaries to prove the Deity of the Holy Spirit; toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with an Anſwer to their grand Objection touching the ſuppoſed Omnipreſence of the Holy Spirit.</p>
            <p>By IOHN BIDLE, Maſter of Arts.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 Theſſ. 5.21.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prove all things, hold faſt that which is good.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Yeare 1647.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:114544:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:114544:2"/>
            <head>To the impartiall READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I conſider with my ſelfe, how many Truths have (in their dawnings) gone forth like the Morning, and are now riſen unto a glorious day, unto the amazement, and confounding of thoſe, who were grand Oppoſers of them; (though I know truth hath, and ſtill ſhall have many Adverſaries; whilſt the face of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering, and the vaile ſpread over all Nations remains un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtroyed; yet I know too, that Truth's bare breaſts are Armour of Prooff againſt all the daring darts of Satan, and all the furious attempts and ſtormes of the fleſh) I cannot but abundantly rejoyce in the glory of its ſtrength. How many things have in ſeverall Ages (as well as in Ours) been cryed up for truths? And how hath God blown upon them, that they have withered, and the whirlewind hath taken them away as ſtuble? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, how many Truths have been cryed down as Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphemy and Errour, the beames of whoſe glory, are now ready to dazell and obſcure all the glory of the fleſh? Sometimes taking in thoſe (through the goings forth of God in it,) who have bin the mightieſt enemies, inſomuch that (ſtanding amazed awhile) they have ſoon been ſwallowed up in the power of it: And oh that mine eyes might behold more of that day of Gods power, and of the out-lettings of the beauties of his holineſſe; that the tall Cedars of <hi>Lebanon</hi> might be bended, and the Oakes of <hi>Baſhan</hi> aſhamed, that the creature and its glory might be brought low, and men who are now like Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locks unaccuſtomed unto the yoak, might be made wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and the Lord alone exalted in them, by them, and amongſt them.</p>
            <p>Did we but ſeriouſly conſider, how moſt men are
<pb facs="tcp:114544:3"/>adorned with living names, (<hi>viz.</hi> of Believers, Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Proteſtants, &amp;c.) whilſt they are indeed dead, (as will appear, ſeeing there are no ſymptoms of life in them) we could not but ſtartle at it: what is the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or Religion, of moſt part of men, but formall and fleſhly? Are they not like thoſe barbarous <hi>Lettoes,</hi> who who were alwayes in the Fields and Woods, heard ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering theſe words, <hi>feru feru Maſco Lon:</hi> but being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the reaſon, they Replyed, <hi>That they knew no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but that they had bin ſo of long taught by their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtours:</hi> Mens mouthes are now filled with Forms, and they are daily crying out the Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord; God, and Chriſt, and Spirit; when tis evident, they have no more then what Education affords, nay leſſe, becauſe not moralized, wherein Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens out-ſtrip them, they know not God, did they, they could not lightly blaſpheme him; they goe Chriſtleſſe, and have not received the Spirit of wiſdome in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation and knowledge of him; and this makes them to cry out, that whatſoever is not according to their fleſhly Formes, is Error, Hereſie, Blaſphemie, becauſe it will not hold according to carnall principals, unto which they muſt needs reduce all things, who have no princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall of life within them; ſuch are thoſe who are called Chriſtians, and yet reel too and fro through wine and ſtrong drink, and ſwell by reaſon of Oathes, living in abominations; of which ſort of men moſt of our Pariſh Churches are conſtituted: ſuch men have not diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſpirits, neither are they competent judges, becauſe enemies to Truth, as well as Errour, wherefore the Author betakes himſelf to the Chriſtian Reader, <hi>i.e.</hi> one that is ſo indeed.</p>
            <p>I know many men (as well as my ſelfe) will be ready to cry out Blaſphemy, Blaſphemy at the firſt view of the
<pb facs="tcp:114544:3"/>Title Page, yet I could wiſh that they would embrace the Apoſtles counſell, <hi>Prove all things, holding faſt that which is good:</hi> Call all things to a ſerious examine, and reject no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing hand over-head, take nothing upon Truſt, without a fore-examining of every circumſtance, leſt in the one, they ſhould reject Truth inſtead of Errour; and in the other, embrace Errour inſtead of truth.</p>
            <p>The Authour hath a long time waited upon learned men for a ſatisfactory Anſwer to theſe Arguments, but hath received none, his hopes are, that the publiſhing of them will be a meanes to produce it, that he may receive ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, and others may be held no longer in ſuſpence, who are in travell with an earneſt expectation of a ſpeedy reſolution, as well as he. I ſhould deſire thoſe who view it, but eſpecially thoſe who undertake to Anſwer it (for my hopes are, that ſome one will) to conſider; firſt, that to ſay, ſuch an Argument is invalid, and weak, and not worth the Anſwering, is no convincing way of arguing, nor able to yeild the leaſt ſatisfaction to a doubting ſpirit. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that invectives, railings or reproachfull termes, are no convincing Arguments (as all men of a ſober judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment well know;) at theſe rates the weakeſt man may ſubvert the ſtrongeſt Controverſie, yet theſe have been the arguings of our times, both in Preſſe and Pulpit. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to prohibite the progreſſe of it, can no wayes unſcruple doubting ſpirits, amongſt whom (for the preſent) I number my ſelfe, expecting an Anſwer to theſe enſuing Arguments; and that God will be with him that undertakes it, and give in a ſpirit of Meekneſſe, and of Wiſdome, in the Revelation and Knowledge of Truth, ſhall be the matter of his prayers, who deſires Truth may be cleared up, and ſhine like the noone-day, and all Errour confounded, and vaniſh before Truth, like a miſt before the Sunne.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:114544:4"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>CHriſtian Reader, I beſeech thee, as thou tendereſt thy ſalvation, that thou wouldeſt thoroughly examine the following Diſputation, in the feare of God, conſidering how much his glory is concerned therein, and at any hand forbeare to condemn my Opinion as Erroneous, till thou art able to bring per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent and ſolid Anſwers to all my Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; for thou muſt know, that though I have conteſted with ſundry Learned men, yet hath none hitherto produced a ſatisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Anſwer to ſo much as one Argument.</hi> Farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I.B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:114544:4"/>
            <head>A LETTER written to a certain Knight, a Member of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Houſe of Commons.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving now attended for the ſpace of ſixteen Months, partly in the Country, and partly in <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> that I might come to my Anſwer before the <hi>Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament,</hi> and finding after all this tarriance, that I am ſtill as farre from having my cauſe determined, as ever, I am even forced to make my addreſſe to you, and to beſeech you, if you have any bowels towards them that are in miſery, that you would either procure my diſcharge, or at leaſt make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port to the Houſe touching my deniall of the ſuppoſed Deity of the Holy Spirit. For that this only is the matter in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation you very well know, having both heard my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion before the Committee, and remembring how when I was urged to declare my judgement concerning the Deity of Chriſt, I waved the queſtion, as neither being that I was accuſed of, nor which I had yet ſufficiently ſtudyed to engage my ſelfe publickly therein. As for my opinion touching the Holy Spirit, it is thus; I believe the Holy Spirit to be the chiefe of all
<note n="a" place="margin">ſee Heb. 1.13.14. whence theſe words are borrowed; and compare it with 1 Pet. .1 12. as alſo Heb. 1.7. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with Acts 1.2, 3.4. and it will ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily appeare that the Holy Spirit is a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of God, as well as others.</note> Miniſtring Spirits, peculiarly ſent out from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to miniſter on their behalfe that ſhall inherit ſalvation; and I do place him both according to the Scripture, and the Primitive Chriſtians, and by name <hi>Iustin Martyr</hi> in his <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology,</hi> in the third ranke after God and Chriſt, giving him a preheminence above all the reſt of the Heavenly Hoſt; So that as there is one principall Spirit amongſt the evill Angels, known in the Scripture by the name of <hi>Satan</hi> or the
<note n="b" place="margin">1 Pet. 5.8.</note> 
               <hi>Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary,</hi> or <hi>the
<note n="c" place="margin">Zech. 13.2.</note> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleane Spirit,</hi> or <hi>the
<note n="d" place="margin">1 Sam. 16.15.16.</note> Evill Spirit of God,</hi> or
<note n="e" place="margin">ib. ver. the laſt.</note> 
               <hi>the Spirit</hi> of God, or
<note n="f" place="margin">1 Kings 12.21. according to the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.</note> 
               <hi>the Spirit</hi> by way of eminence: Even ſo is there one principall Spirit; (I borrow this Appellation from the Septuagint, who render the latter clauſe of the 12
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:114544:5"/>verſe of Pſal. 31. in this manner, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Spiritu principali fulci me,</hi> ſtabliſh me with thy principall Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,) there is, I ſay, one principall Spirit amongſt the good Angels, called by the name of <hi>the
<note n="g" place="margin">Iohn 16.7.</note> Advocate,</hi> or <hi>the
<note n="h" place="margin">Eph. 4.30.</note> Holy ſpirit,</hi> or
<note n="i" place="margin">Neh. 9.20.</note> 
               <hi>the good ſpirit of God,</hi> or
<note n="k" place="margin">1 Cot. 7.40.</note> 
               <hi>the ſpirit of God,</hi> or
<note n="l" place="margin">Acts 10.19.</note> 
               <hi>the ſpirit,</hi> by way of eminence. This opinion of mine is atteſted by the whole tenour of the Scripture, which perpetually ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of him as differing from God, and inferiour to him, but is irrefragably proved by theſe places of Scripture, Neh. 9.6.20. <hi>Thou, even thou art Lord (or Iehovah) alone, thou haſt made Heaven, the Heaven of Heavens, with all their Hoſt. Thou gaveſt thy good ſpirit to inſtruct them (the Children of Iſrael.)</hi>] Iohn 16.7.8. &amp;c. <hi>Nevertheleſſe, I tell you the truth, it is expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient for you that I goe away: for if I goe not away the
<note n="m" place="margin">So the word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in the Originall perpetually ſignifieth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Greek Authours, and is ſo rendred by the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlatours them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. 1 Iohn 2.1. and ought to have been ſo rendred here, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe he ſaith in the following words, that the Holy Spirit ſhall convince the world, for it is proper to an Advocate to convince.</note> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate will not come unto you, but if I depart I will ſend him unto you. And when hee is come, hee will reprove</hi> (in the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, <hi>Convince</hi>) <hi>the world of ſinne, and of righteouſneſſe, and of judgement. I have yet many things, to ſay unto you, but yee cannot beare them now. Howbeit when he, the ſpirit of truth, is come, he will guide you into all truth; for he ſhall not ſpeake of himſelfe, but whatſoever he ſhall heare, that ſhall he ſpeake; and he will ſhew you things to come. He ſhall glorifie me, for he ſhall receive of mine and ſhall ſhew it unto you. All things that the Father hath, are mine: therefore ſaid I, he ſhall take of mine, and ſhew it unto you.</hi>] Rom. 8.26, 27. <hi>Likewiſe the ſpirit alſo helpeth our infirmities; for we know not what wee ſhould pray for as wee ought: but the ſpirit himſelfe maketh interceſſion for us, with grones that cannot be uttered. But he that ſearcheth the hearts, knoweth what is the minde (or deſire) of the ſpirit, for he maketh interceſſion for the Saints according to the will of God.</hi>] Acts 19.2. <hi>And (Paul) finding certaine Diſciples, ſaid unto them, have yee received the Holy Spirit, ſince yee believed? And they ſaid unto him, we have not ſo much as heard whether there be any Holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi>] Eph. 4.4.5.6. <hi>There is one body, and one ſpirit, even as yee have been called in one hope of your calling. One Lord, one faith, one Baptiſme. One God and Father of all, who is above all, and through all, and in you all.</hi>] 1 Cor. 12.3.4. <hi>&amp;c. Wherefore I give you to underſtand, that noman ſpeaking by the ſpirit of God, calleth
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114544:5"/>Jeſus accurſed, and that no man can ſay that Ieſus is the Lord, but by the Holy ſpirit; But there are diverſities of gifts, yet the ſame ſpirit. And there are diverſities of administrations, yet the ſame Lord; And there are diverſities of operations, yet it is the ſame God that worketh all in all.</hi>] Luke 3.21, 22. <hi>It came to paſſe that Ieſus alſo being baptized, and praying, the Heaven was opened, and the Holy ſpirit deſcended in a bodily ſhape like a dove upon him.</hi>] 1 Cor. 2.11.12.13. <hi>But God hath revealed them to us by his ſpirit, for the ſpirit ſearcheth all things, even the depths of God. For what man knoweth the things of a man ſave the ſpirit of a man, which is in him? even ſo the things of God knoweth none, but the ſpirit of God,</hi> (he doth not adde, as before, <hi>which is in him.) Now we have received, not the ſpirit of the world, but the ſpirit which is of God, that we might know the things that are freely given us of God.</hi> Revel. 22.12.17. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I come quickly, and my reward is with me, to give unto every man according as his work ſhall be, and the Spirit and the Bride ſay, come.</hi>] Acts 5.32. <hi>And wee are his witneſſes of theſe things, and ſo is alſo the Holy Spirit, whom God hath given to them that obey him.</hi>] Gal. 3.5. <hi>He therefore that miniſtreth (or giveth) to you the Spirit, and worketh miracles among you, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th he it by the works of the Law, or by the hearing (or rather preaching of Faith.</hi>] <hi>He that ministreth or giveth the ſpirit to you,</hi> a ſtrange kinde of ſpeech, if the Holy Spirit were God. The Scripture is wont to ſpeak more ſoberly of Almighty God, then to ſay that he is given by another, much leſſe by men, as it is here ſaid of the Holy Spirit, 1 Cor. 8.4.5.6. [<hi>Wee know that an Idoll is nothing in the world, and that there is no other God but one. For though there be that are called Gods, whether in Heaven, or in Earth; as there be many Gods, and many Lords, yet unto us there is but one God, ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the Father, of whom are all things, and wee unto him; and one Lord, even Ieſus Chriſt, by whom are all things, and wee by him.</hi>] You ſee here that the Apoſtle being about to ſet down, who is the only God, and only Lord of Chriſtians, maketh no mention of the Holy Spirit, which could not have been done by ſo faithfull an Apoſtle, had the Holy Spirit bin either God or Lord. Of theſe places thus recited no man, though never ſo ſubtile, and though he turn and winde
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114544:6"/>his wit every way, ſhall ever be able to make ſence, unleſſe he take the Holy Spirit to be what I ſay.</p>
            <p>Behold now the cauſe for which I have lyen under perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, raiſed againſt me by my adverſaries, who being unable to juſtifie by Argument their practice of giving glory to the Holy Spirit, as God, in the end of their prayers, ſince there is neither precept nor example for it in all the Scripture; and being taxed by me for giving the glory of God to another, and worſhipping what he hath not commanded, nor ever came into his heart, have in a cruell and unchriſtian manner reſorted to the arme of fleſh, and inſtigated the Magiſtrate againſt me, hoping by his ſword, (not that of the Spirit) to uphold their Will-worſhip; but in vaine, ſince every Plant that the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father hath not ſet, ſhall be rooted up; and that this practice of Worſhipping the Holy Spirit as God, is ſuch a Plant as God never ſet in his word, would ſoone appeare to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Houſe, could they be but ſo farr prevailed with, as, laying aſide all prejudice, ſeriouſly to weigh the many and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid proofes that I produce for my opinion out of the Scripture, together with the ſleight, or rather no proofes of the adverſe party for their opinion, which they themſelves know not what to make of, but that they endeavour to delude both themſelves and others with Perſonalities, Moods, Subſiſtences, and ſuch like brainſick Notions, that have neither ſap nor ſence in them, and were firſt hatched by the ſubtilty of Satan in the heads of Platoniſts, to pervert the Worſhip of the true God. Neither could this controverſy be ſet on foot in a fitter juncture of time then this, wherein the Parliament and Kingdome have ſolemnly engaged themſelves to reſorme Religion both in Diſcipline and Doctrine. For amongſt all the corruptions in Doctrine, which certainly are many, there is none that more deſerveth to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended then this, that ſo palpably thwarteth the whole tenour of the Scripture, and trencheth to the very object of our wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and therefore ought not to be lightly paſſed over by any man that profeſſeth himſelfe a Chriſtian, much more a Reformer. God is jealous of his honour, and will not give it to another, we therefore as beloved children ſhould imitate our heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther herein, and not upon any pretence whatſoever depart from
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114544:6"/>his expreſſe command, and give the worſhip of the ſupreame Lord of Heaven and Earth, to him whom the Scripture no where affirmeth to be God. For my own particular, after a long and impartiall enquiry of the truth, in this controverſy, and after much and earneſt calling upon God to give unto me the ſpirit of wiſedom and revelation in the knowledg of him, I findemy ſelfe obliged both by the principles of Scripture and of Reaſon to embrace the opinion I now hold forth, and as much as in me lyeth, to endeavour that the honour of Almighty God be not transferred to another, not only to the offence of God himſelfe, but alſo of his Holy Spirit, who cannot but be grieved to have that ignorantly aſcribed to himſelfe, which is proper to God that ſends him, and which he no where challengeth to himſelfe in the Scripture: what ſhall befall me in purſuance of this worke, I referre to the diſpoſall of the all-wiſe God, whoſe glory is dearer to me, not only then my liberty, but then my life. It will be your part, Honoured Sir, into whoſe hands God hath put ſuch an opportunity, to examine the buſineſſe impartially, and to be an helper to the truth, conſidering that this controverſy is of the greateſt importance in the world, and that the divine truth ſuffers not her ſelfe to be deſpiſed ſcot-free. Neither let the meaneſſe of my outward preſence deterr you from ſtirring, ſince it is the part of a wiſe man, as in all things, ſo eſpecially in matters of Religion, not to regard ſo much who it is that ſpeaketh, as what it is that is ſpoken, remembring how our Saviour in the Goſpell ſaith that God is wont to hide his ſecrets from the wiſe and prudent, and to reveale them unto children. In which number I willingly reckon my ſelfe, being couſcious of mine own perſonall weakneſſe, but well aſſured of the ſtrength and evidence of the Scripture to beare me out in this cauſe; and remain</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Aprill</hi> 1. 1647.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Yours in the Lord, <hi>I. Bidle.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:114544:7"/>
            <head>Twelve <hi>Arguments</hi> drawn out of the Scripture, wherein the commonly received Opinion touching the Deity of the Holy Spirit, is clearly and fully refuted.</head>
            <div n="1" type="argument">
               <head>ARG<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MENT 1.</head>
               <p>HE that is diſtinguiſhed from God, is not God; the holy Spirit is diſtinguiſhed from God. <hi>Ergo.</hi> The <hi>major</hi> is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, for if he ſhould both b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God, &amp; be diſtinguiſhed from God, he would be diſtinguiſhed from himſelfe, which implyeth a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction. The <hi>minor</hi> is confirmed by the whole currant of the Scripture, which calleth him <hi>the Spirit of God,</hi> and ſaith that <hi>he is ſent by God, and ſearcheth the depths of God &amp;c.</hi> Neither let any man ſee think to fly to that ignorant refuge of making a diſtinction betweene the Eſſence and Perſon of God, ſaying that the Holy Spirit is diſtinguiſhed from God, taken perſonally not Eſſentially. For this wretched diſtinction (to omit the mention of the Primitive Fathers) is not only unheard of in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ſo to be rejected, it being preſumption to affirme any thing of the unſearchable nature of God, which he hath not firſt affirmed of himſelfe in the Scripture: but is alſo diſclaimed by Reaſon For firſt, it is impoſſible for any man, if he would but endeavour to conceive the thing, and not delude both himſelfe and others with empty termes and words without underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, to diſtinguiſh the perſon from the Eſſence of God, and not to frame two beings or things in his minde, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently two Gods. Secondly, If the perſon be diſtinct from the Eſſence of God, then it is either ſomething or nothing: if nothing, how can it be diſtinguiſhed, ſince nothing hath no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents? If ſomething, then either ſome finite or infinite thing; if finite, then there will be ſomething finite in God; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently ſince by the confeſſion of the adverſaryes themſelves, every thing in God is God himſelfe, God will be finite, which the adverſaryes themſelves will likewiſe confeſſe to be abſurd. If infinite, then there will be two infinites in God, to wit the Perſon
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:114544:7"/>and Eſſence of God, and conſequently two Gods; which is more ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd then the former. Thirdly, to talk of God taken only Eſſentially is ridiculous, not only becauſe there is no example thereof in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but becauſe God is the name of a
<note n="*" place="margin">By perſon I underſtand, as Philoſophers doe, <hi>ſuppoſitum intelligens,</hi> that is, an intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual ſubſtance compleat and not a moode or ſubſiſtence, which are fantaſticall and ſenſeleſſe terms, brought in to couzen the ſimple.</note> Perſon, and ſignifieth him that ruleth over others; and when it is put for the moſt high God, it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noteth him who with ſoveraign and abſolute authority ruleth over all; but none but a perſon can rule over others, all actions being proper to perſons: wherefore to take God otherwiſe then perſonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, is to take him otherwiſe then he is, and indeed to miſtake him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="argument">
               <head>ARG<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MENT 2.</head>
               <p>If he that gave the Holy Spirit to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to inſtruct them, be Iehovah alone, then the Holy Spirit is not Iehovah or God; But he that gave the Holy Spirit to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to inſtruct them, is Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah alone; <hi>Ergo.</hi> The ſequele of the <hi>major</hi> is plaine, for if he that gave the Holy Spirit be Iehovah alone, and yet the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit that was given be Iehovah too, the ſame will be Iehovah alone, and not Jehovah alone, which implyeth a contradiction. The <hi>minor</hi> is evidenced by Neh. 9.6.20.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="argument">
               <head>ARG<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MENT 3.</head>
               <p>He that ſpeaketh not of himſelfe, is not God. The Holy Spirit ſpeaketh not of himſelfe; <hi>Ergo.</hi> The <hi>minor</hi> is cleare from Ioh 16.13. The <hi>major</hi> is proved thus: God ſpeaketh of himſelfe; therefore if there be any one that ſpeaketh not of himſelfe, he is not God. The antecedent is of it ſelfe apparant, for God is the primary authour of whatſoever he doth, but ſhould hee not ſpeake of himſelfe, he muſt ſpeake from another, and ſo not be the primary, but ſecundary au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of his ſpeech, which is abſurd, if at leaſt that may be called abſurd, which is impoſſible. The conſequence is undeniable. For further confirmation of this Argument, it is to be obſerved, that to ſpeake or do any thing not of himſelfe, according to the ordinary phraſe of Scripture, is to ſpeake or do by the ſhewing, teaching, commanding, authoriſing, or enabling of another, and conſequently incompatible with the ſupreame and ſelfe-ſufficient Majeſty of God. <hi>Vid.</hi> Iohn 5.19.20.30. 7.15.16.17.18.28. 8.28.42. 11.50. 51. 12.49.50. 14.10.24. 15.4. 18.34. Luke 12.56.57. 21.30. 2 Cor. 3.5.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="argument">
               <head>ARG<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MENT 4.</head>
               <p>He that heareth from another what he ſhall ſpeake, is not God; The Holy ſpirit doth ſo; <hi>Ergo.</hi> The <hi>Minor</hi> is plain from the for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114544:8"/>place Iohn 16.13. The <hi>major</hi> is proved thus; he that is taught, is not God; he that heareth from another what he ſhall ſpeake, is taught; <hi>Ergo.</hi> The <hi>major</hi> is clear by Eſay 40.13.14. compared with Rom. 11.34. 1. Cor. 2.16. The <hi>Minor</hi> is evidenced by Iohn 8. where our Saviour having ſaid in the 26. verſe, <hi>whatſoever I have heard from him (the Father) theſe things I ſpeake;</hi>] in the 28. verſe he expreſſeth the ſame ſence thus; <hi>According as the Father hath taught me, theſe things I ſpeake.</hi> Neither let any man goe about to elude ſo pregnant an Argument, by ſaying that this is ſpoken of the Holy Spirit improperly; For let him turne himſelfe every way, and ſcrue the words as he pleaſe, yet ſhall he never be able to make it out to a wiſe and conſidering man, how it can poſſibly be ſaid that any one heareth from another what he will ſpeake, who is the prime Author of his ſpeech, and into whom it is not at a certaine time inſinuated by another. For this expreſſion plainly intimateth, that whatſoever the Holy Spirit ſpeaketh to the Diſciples, is firſt diſcovered and committed to him by Chriſt, whoſe Embaſſadour he is, it being proper to an Embaſſadour to be the Interpreter not of his own, but of anothers will. But it is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions to imagine that the moſt high God can have any thing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered and committed to him by another.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="argument">
               <head>ARG<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MENT 5.</head>
               <p>He that receiveth of another, is not God; The Holy Spirit doth ſo; <hi>Ergo.</hi> The <hi>Minor</hi> is witneſſed by the aforeſaid place Iohn 16.14. The <hi>Major</hi> is proved thus; God is he that giveth all things to all; wherefore if there be any one that receiveth of anothers, he cannot be God. The antecedent is plaine by Acts 17.25. Rom. 11.35.36. The conſequence is undeniable, for if God ſhould give all things to all, and yet receive of anothers, he would both give all things, and not give all things; which implyeth a contradiction. The <hi>Major</hi> of the Proſyllogiſme is otherwiſe urged thus, He that is dependent, is not God; he that receiveih of anothers, is depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent; <hi>Ergo.</hi> The <hi>Major</hi> is unqueſtionable, for to ſay that one is dependent, and yet God, is in effect to ſay he is God and not God, which implyeth a contradiction. The <hi>Minor</hi> alſo is evident, for to receive of anothers, is the very notion of dependency.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="argument">
               <head>ARG<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MENT 6.</head>
               <p>He that is ſent by another, is not God; the Holy Spirit is ſent by another; <hi>Ergo.</hi> The <hi>Minor</hi> is plaine from the forequoted
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114544:8"/>place Iohn 16.7. The <hi>Major</hi> is evinced thus; he that miniſtreth is not God, he that is ſent miniſtreth; <hi>Ergo.</hi> The <hi>Major</hi> is undubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, it being diſſonant to the ſupreame Majeſty of God to miniſter, and ſerve another, for that were to be God and not God; to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe ſoveraign dominion over all, and not to exerciſe it. The <hi>Minor</hi> is confirmed by Heb. 1. <hi>ult.</hi> where the divine Author ſheweth that the Angels are all Miniſtring Spirits, in that they are ſent forth; as he before intimated Chriſt to be Lord, becauſe he ſitteth at the right hand of God. Thus <hi>David</hi> Pſal. 2. declareth the Soveraignty of God, in ſaying that he ſitteth in Heaven. The <hi>Minor</hi> is further proved thus; He that receiveth a command for the performance of ſomething, doth Miniſter; He that is ſent forth, receiveth a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand for the performance of ſomething; <hi>Ergo.</hi> The <hi>Major</hi> is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to common ſence, ſince it ſuiteth with none but miniſters and inferiours to receive commands. The <hi>Minor</hi> is manifeſt by Iohn 12.49. <hi>The Father that hath ſent me, he gave me a Command what I ſhall ſpeake.</hi>] Neither let any man here reply that this very thing is ſpoken alſo of Chriſt, unleſſe, having firſt proved that Chriſt is ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame God, he will grant that whatſoever is ſpoken of him, is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of him as God: or can make good that to be ſent at leaſt may agree to him as God. The contrary whereof I ſuppoſe I have clearely proved in this Argument, ſhewing that it is unſutable to the divine Majeſty.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="argument">
               <head>ARG<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MENT 7.</head>
               <p>He that is the giſt of God, is not God; The Holy Spirit is the gift of God; <hi>Ergo.</hi> The <hi>minor</hi> is plain by Acts 11.17. <hi>For as much then as God gave them the like gift</hi> (meaning the Spirit) <hi>as he did unto us, who have believed on the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, was I one that could withſtand God?</hi> The <hi>Major</hi> though of it ſelfe ſufficiently cleare, is yet further evidenced thus; he that is not the giver of all things, is not God; he that is the gift of God, is not the giver of all things; <hi>Ergo.</hi> the <hi>major</hi> is apparent from Acts 17.25. <hi>God giveth to all, life, breath, and all things.</hi> The <hi>Minor</hi> is proved thus; he that is himſelfe given, is not the giver of all things; he that is the gift of God, is himſelfe gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; <hi>Ergo.</hi> The <hi>major</hi> is undeniable, for otherwiſe the ſame would be the giver of all things, and yet not the giver of all things, inaſmuch as he himſelfe, a principall thing, is giver, which implyeth a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction. The <hi>minor</hi> needeth no proofe. Moreover, a gift is in the power, and at the diſpoſall of the giver; but it is groſſe and abſurd to imagine that God can be in the power, or at the diſpoſall of another,
<pb facs="tcp:114544:9"/>Neither let any man here think to evade by ſaying, that not the Holy Spirit himſelfe, but only his gifts are imparted to men; Since both the more learned adverſaryes themſelves confeſſe, that the Perſon of of the Holy Spirit is given together with his gifts, and the Scripture putteth the matter out of doubt if you conſult Neh. 9.20. and Rom. 5.5. In both which places, the Holy Spirit is ſaid to be given con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiſtinctly from his gifts and operations; in the firſt, contradiſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly from the inſtruction flowing from him; in the other, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſtinctly from the love of God diffuſed in our hearts by him. Whence we may draw this Corollary, that if the Perſon of the Holy Spirit be out of favour given to certaine men, as the aforeſaid places teſtify, then he was not perſonally preſent with them before, and conſequently by the conceſſion of the adverſaries themſelves, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be God, ſince they will not deny that God is alwayes perſonally preſent with all alike. But I foreſtall the following Argument.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="argument">
               <head>ARG<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MENT 8.</head>
               <p>He that changeth place, is not God; The Holy Spirit changeth place; <hi>Ergo.</hi> The <hi>major</hi> is plaine, for if God ſhould change place, he would ceaſe to be where he was before, and begin to be where he was not before, which everteth his Omnipreſence, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, by the confeſſion of the adverſaries themſelves, his Deity. The <hi>minor</hi> is ocularly apparant, if following the
<note n="*" place="margin">Abi, Aria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, ad Iorda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, &amp; Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem videbis.</note> adviſe of the adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, you wil but go to Iordan, for there you ſhal have the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in a bodily ſhape deſcending from heaven, which is the <hi>terminus à quo,</hi> alighting upon Chriſt, which is the <hi>terminus ad quem,</hi> Luke 3 21.22. Neither let any man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lledge, that as much is ſpoken of God. Exod 3. &amp; chap. 20. &amp; Gen. 18. For if you compare Acts 7.30.35.38.53. Gal. 3.19. Heb. 2.2.3. &amp; chap. 13.2. with the foreſaid places, you ſhall finde, that it was not God himſelfe that came down, but only an Angel, ſuſtaining the Perſon and Name of God; which hath no place in the hiſtory, touching the deſcent of the Holy Spirit</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="argument">
               <head>ARG<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MENT 9.</head>
               <p>He that prayeth unto Chriſt, to come to judgement, is not God; The Holy Spirit doth ſo; <hi>Ergo.</hi> The <hi>maior</hi> is granted. The <hi>minor</hi> is evident from Rev. 22.17. compared with 12. verſe. Neither let any man think to elude this proofe, by ſaying, that the Spirit is here ſaid to pray, only becauſe he maketh the Bride to pray. For when the Scripture would ſignify the aſſiſtance of the Holy Spirit in cauſing men to ſpeake, it is wont to affirme, either that the Holy Spirit ſpeaketh in them, as Matth. 10.20. or that they ſpeake by the Holy Spirit, as Rom. 8.15. <hi>Wee have received the Spirit of adoption, by whom wee cry Abba Father.</hi>] But here it is expreſſely ſaid, that the Spirit and the Bride ſay, <hi>come;</hi> not the Spirit in the Bride, not the Bride by the Spirit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="argument">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:114544:9"/>
               <head>ARG. 10.</head>
               <p>He in whom men have not believed, and yet have been Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples and Believers, is not God; Men have not believed in the Holy Spirit, and yet have been ſo; <hi>Ergo:</hi> The major is plain, for how can any be Diſciples and Believers, according to the phraſe of Scripture, and not believe in Him that is God? The minor is proved thus, Men have not ſo much as heard whether there were an Holy Spirit, and yet have been Diſciples and Believers; <hi>Ergo:</hi> They have not believed in the Holy Spirit, and yet have been Diſciples and Believers. The Antecedent is apparant from <hi>Acts</hi> 19.2. The conſequence is grounded on that of the Apoſtle <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.14. [How ſhall they believe on Him, of whom they have not heard?] Now if any man to decline the dint of this Argument, ſhall ſay, that by Holy Spirit in theſe words [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] is meant not the Perſon, but the Gifts of the Holy Spirit, He, beſides that hee perverteth the plaine and genuine meaning of the words, and ſpeaketh with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out example, doth alſo evacuate the emphaſis of the Particles <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which emply that theſe Diſciple were ſo far from ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving received the Gifts of the Holy Spirit, whereof we may grant that the queſtion made mention, that they had not ſo much as heard whether there were an Holy Spirit or not. Again, that the Holy Spirit is not God, doth further appear by this very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, ſince the Apoſtle, when there was ſo ample an occaſion offered to declare it, (if it had been ſo) doth quite decline it: For it is incredible that He, who was ſo intent and vigilant in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagating the Truth, as that caſually ſeeing an Altar at <hi>Athens</hi> inſcribed to the unknown God, he preſently took a hint from thence to preach unto the Heathens the true God; yet here being told by Diſciples that they had not ſo much as heard whether there were an Holy Spirit, or not, ſhould not make uſe of the opportunity to diſcover unto Them and in Them to Us, the (Deity of the Holy Spirit, but ſuffer them to remaine in igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance touching a point of ſuch conſequence, that without the knowledge thereof (if we believe many now now adayes) men cannot be ſaved. Certainly, the Apoſtle had a greater care both of the Truth of God, and the ſalvation of men, then to do ſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="argument">
               <head>ARG. 11.</head>
               <p>He that hath an underſtanding diſtinct from that of God, is
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:114544:10"/>not God; The Holy Spirit hath an underſtanding diſtinct from God; <hi>Ergo:</hi> The major is clear; for he that hath an underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſtinct from that of another, muſt needs likewiſe have a diſtinct Eſſence, wherein that underſtanding may reſide. The minor is proved thus, He that heareth from God, and that at the ſecond hand, what he ſhall ſpeak, hath an underſtanding di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from that of God; The Holy Spirit ſo heareth from God; <hi>Ergo:</hi> the minor is evident from <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.13, 14, 15. The major is confirmed thu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; He that is taught of God, hath an under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding diſtinct from that of God; He that heareth from God, is taught of God; <hi>Ergo:</hi> The minor is manifeſt from <hi>John</hi> 8. where our Saviour Chriſt having ſaid in the Verſe 26. <hi>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſoever I have heard from him</hi> (the Father) <hi>theſe things I ſpeak:</hi>] In Verſe 28. he expreſſeth the ſame ſence thus, [<hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as the Father hath taught me, theſe things I ſpeak.</hi>] The major is of it ſelfe clear; for he that is taught, hath an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowing underſtanding, ſince none can be taught what hee knoweth already; and he that teacheth hath a knowing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, otherwiſe he could not teach another ſomething; but it emplyeth a contradiction that the ſame underſtanding ſhould at the ſame time be both knowing and unknowing of the ſame thing. Beſides, that the Holy Spirit hath an under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding diſtinct from that of God, is eaſily deducible from the words of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10. where he affirmeth, that the Spirit ſearcheth the depths of God, (as <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.27. he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timateth, that God ſearcheth the heart of the Spirit:) but to ſearch the depths of any one neceſſarily ſuppoſeth one under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in him that ſearcheth, and another underſtanding in him whoſe depths are ſearched, as is evident not only by colla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of other places of the Scripture, as 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.11. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.13. but even by common ſenſe, dictating to every man ſo much, that none can without abſurdity be ſaid to ſearch the depths of his own underſtanding. Whence the Apoſtle going about to illuſtrate what he had ſpoken of the Spirit of God, by a ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude drawn from the ſpirit of a man, doth not ſay, that the ſpirit of a man doth ſearch, but know the things of a man, though his former words did ſeem to lead him thereunto.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="argument">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:114544:10"/>
               <head>ARG. 12.</head>
               <p>He that hath a will diſtinct in number from that of God, is not God; The Holy Spirit hath a will diſtinct in number from that of God, <hi>Ergo.</hi> The major is irrefragable: The minor is aſſerted thus; He that willeth conformably to the will of God, hath a will diſtinct in number from that of God; The Holy Spirit ſo w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lleth; <hi>Ergo:</hi> The major is plaine, for conformity muſt be between two at leaſt, elſe it will not be conformity, but identity. The minor is confirmed by <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26.27. [Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Spirit alſo helpeth our infirmities, for we know not what to pray for as we ought, but the Spirit himſelfe maketh interceſſion for us with groanes unutterable; But he that ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the heart, knoweth what is the minde (or will) of the Spirit, for he maketh interceſſion for the Saints according to (or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formably to) the will of God.] Which words of the Apoſtle afford us another impregnable Argument of the Holy Spirit's being inferiour to God, inaſmuch as he is ſaid to make inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion unto God (as wee before urged his praying to Chriſt, <hi>Arg.</hi> 9.) and that with groanes unutterable; which is not ſo to be underſtood as if the Holy Spirit were here ſaid to help our infirmities only by ſuggeſting petitions and groans unto us, and making us to pray, (as is commonly, but falſely affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,) for the very words of the context ſufficiently refute ſuch a gloſſe, ſince they ſay that the Spirit himſelf, not we by the Spirit, (as we have it in verſe 15. of the ſame chap.) maketh interceſſion for us: but to help others infirmities by making interceſſion for them, is not to inſtill petitions into them, but to pour out petitions apart in their behalf, as is apparant both from the thing it ſelfe (ſince none can intercede for himſelfe, all interceſſion requiring the enterm ſe of a third perſon:) and by the collation of verſe 34. of the ſame chapter, and by the 30. ver. of the 15. chap. and by 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.11. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Col.</hi> 4.12. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.18. Neither let any man think to bafflle off this Argument, which is written with a beame of the Sun, by ſaying that this is improperly ſpoken of the Hol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Spirit; for, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that he hath no other ground to ſay ſo, but his own pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceived opinion touching the Diety of the of Holy Spirit, he ought to know that the Scripture, though it ſpeaketh many things after the manner of men, yet doth it no where ſpeak
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:114544:11"/>any thing that argueth his inferiority to, and dependence on another. But this paſſage of the Apoſtle plainly intimateth the Holy Spirit to be inferiour to God, and dependent on him; otherwiſe what need had he to intercede with God, and that with groanes unutterable, on the behalfe of the Saints?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="exposition">
               <head>An Expoſition of <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19.</head>
               <p>[Goe ye therefore, and make Diſciples (ſo it is in the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall) of all Nations, baptiſing them into the name (ſo is it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in the Originall) of the Father, and of the Sonne, and of the Holy Spirit.]</p>
               <p>In the name of the Holy Spirit] that is, into the Holy Spirit, by a circumlocution uſuall in the Scripture, <hi>vid. Acts</hi> 19.5. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3. And into the Holy Spirit, that is, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the guidance of the Holy Spirit. Thus the Iewes are ſaid to have been all baptized into <hi>Moſes,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.2. So that our Saviour's words amount to thus much; initiating them into the confeſſion and obedience of God the Father, and of the Lord Ieſu; Chriſt, the Son of the Father, and of the Holy Spirit the Advocate and guide of all truth. Now the Holy Spirit is mentioned together with God and Chriſt, becauſe he is the chiefe Inſtrument whereby they guide govern, ſanctifie and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow the Church; and to intimate, that whereas men, before they gave their names to Chriſt, lived according to the Prince of this world, the uncleane Spirit, that worketh in the children of diſobedience, they ought henceforth, being ſequeſtred from the world, and admitted into the Church to reſign up themſelves to the guidance of the Holy Spirit, whom God and Chriſt have appointed to order and direct the Church. For that the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit is not ranked with the Father and the Son as being equall to them, is evident by other punctuall places of the Scripture, as 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.3, 4, 5, 6. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.4, 5, 6. where when the mention of him, is joyned with that of the Father and the Son, he is expreſly and emphatically excluded from being either God or Lord, by being contra-diſtinguiſhed from both. But if he be neither God nor Lord, as the Apoſtle not only in theſe places, but elſewhere clearly teſtifies, <hi>vid.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.5.6. he cannot be equall to the Father and the Son, but is only the chiefe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:114544:11"/>of Both, peculiarly ſent our to Miniſter on their behalfe that ſhall inherit ſalvation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="exposition">
               <head>An Expoſition of 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.7.</head>
               <p>[For there are three that beare record in Heaven, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Word, and the Holy Spirit, and theſe three are one.]</p>
               <p>It would have been hard, if not impoſſible, (had not men bin precorrupted) that it ſhould ever come into any ones head to imagine, that this phraſe <hi>are one</hi>] did ſignifie [have one Eſſence,] ſince ſuch an Expoſition is not only contrary to common ſence, but alſo to other places of the Scripture, wherein this kind of ſpeaking prepetually ſignifyeth an union in conſent and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or the like, but never an union in Eſſence. To omit other Sacred Writers, this very Apoſtle in his Goſpel, chap. 17. ver. 11.21, 22, 23. uſeth the ſame expreſſion ſix times, intimating no other but an union of agreement; yea, in verſ. 8. of this very chapter in his Epiſtle, he uſeth it in the ſame ſence. For though the expreſſion varieth ſomewhat in the ordinary Greek Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in that the prepoſition [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] is prefixed, (although the Complutenſian Bible readeth it [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] in both verſes:) yet is the ſence the ſame; this latter being ſpoken after the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew idiome, the former according to the ordinary phraſe; for confirmation whereof ſee <hi>Matth.</hi> 19. comparing verſe 5. &amp; 6. together in the Originall; wherefore this expreſſion ought to be rendred alike in both verſes, as the former Interpreters did it, though the Latter Interpreters, in verſ. 8. have rendred it [<hi>agree in one</hi>] putting the gloſſe inſtead of the Tranſlation. So that this place maketh nothing for them that hold the Holy Spirit to have one and the ſame Eſſence with the Father, unleſſe they can prove that thoſe who are one in agreement muſt likewiſe neceſſarily be one in Eſſence; or that two or three cannot bee one, but it muſt preſently be in Eſſence. I omit for the preſent to ſpeak of the ſuſpectedneſſe of this place, how it is not extant in the ancient Greek Coppies, nor in the Syriack Tranſlation, nor in moſt ancient Books of the Latine Edition, and rejected by ſundry Interpreters both Ancient and Mordern.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="exposition">
               <head>An Expoſition of <hi>Acts</hi> 5.3.4.</head>
               <p>[But <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid, <hi>Ananias,</hi> Why hath Satan filled thy heart to lie to, (or deceive) the Holy Spirit, and to keep back part of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:114544:12"/>the price of the Land? while it remained, was it not thine own? And after it was ſold, was it not in thine own power? Why haſt thou conceived this thing in thine heart? thou haſt not lyed unto men, but unto God.]</p>
               <p>In this paſſage the Holy Spirit is neither expreſly, nor by good conſequence called God. For admit the ordinary Tranſlation were true, (as it is not) yet will it not preſently follow, becauſe <hi>Ananias</hi> by lying to men endued with the Holy Spirit (for even <hi>Piſcator</hi> in the words acknowledgeth, and the words them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, according to this Interpretation, emply a metonymie of the adjunct) lyed not to men, but to God, that therefore the Holy Spirit is God; for in lying to them that are endued with the Spirit of God, one may lie to God, and yet neither they, nor the Spirit in them be God, but only the Meſſengers of God; for what is done to Meſſengers redounds to him that ſendeth them. ſee 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.8. <hi>John</hi> 13.20. <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.16. But if any man look more narrowly into the words, he ſhall perceive that the verbe [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] is conſtrued in a different manner, to wit, with an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſative in verſe 3. and with a dative in verſe 4. Now [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] with an accuſative in Greek Authors is the ſame with [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] that is, to bely, or counterfeit; thus <hi>Lucan in Pſeu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>nomen quoddam mentitus,</hi> counterfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a certaine name. This being ſo, the words are to be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thus, [Why hath Satan filled thy heart to bely or coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit the Holy Spirit? (that is, why haſt thou ſuffered the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean ſpirit ſo farre to prevail with thee, as to lay down this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny at his ſuggeſtion, as appeareth, in that thou haſt proloyned part of the price of thy Poſſeſſion, and not laid down all: and yet to bear us in hand, that thou, as well as others, didſt it at the motion of the Holy Spirit?) Thou haſt not lyed to men, but to God: (that is, aſſure thy ſelfe that this deſſembling of thine is not ſo much to us, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s to God himſelfe, whoſe ſervants wee are.) This Expoſition is not only agreeable to the Greek con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text, and ſcope of the place, but is a alſo ſeconded by <hi>Eraſmus, Calvin,</hi> and <hi>Aretius.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="exposition">
               <head>An Expoſition of 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.19, 20.</head>
               <p>[What? know ye not, that your Body is the Temple of the Holy Spirit, that is in you, whom you have of God, and that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:114544:12"/>ye are not your own? For ye have been bought with a price: wherefore glorifie God both in your body, and in your Spirit, which are God's.]</p>
               <p>Whereas it is objected by ſome out of this paſſage, that the Holy Spirit is God, in that our Body is ſaid to be his Temple: I Anſwer, that it would follow, could it be proved that our body is ſo the Temple of the Holy Spirit, as to be his by intereſt, and dedicated to his honour, both which are in the following words affirmed of God contra-diſtinctly from the Holy Spirit. But theſe things are ſo farre from being held forth in this place, that the contrary may thence not obſcurely be evinced. For the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, after he had intimated in what reſpect our body is the Temple of the Holy Spirit, to wit, by inhabitation, (for ſo much is emplyed by the deſcription, added to the Holy Spirit, ſince deſcriptions in Sacred Writers are not idle and impertinent) he addeth that wee have Him from God, thereby not only diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing Him from God, but intimating alſo that He is deſpoſed of by God, and beſtowed on Us, and conſequently that He is ours by intereſt, and not we his, as the objection would inferre.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="exposition">
               <head>An Expoſition of <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.31.</head>
               <p>[All manner of ſinne and blaſphemy ſhall be forgiven unto men; but the blaſphemy againſt the Spirit ſhall not be forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto men.]</p>
               <p>For the Objection drawn hence, that the ſin againſt the Holy Spirit is unpardonable: I Anſwer, that the ſin againſt the Holy Spirit is not therefore unpardonable, becauſe he is God, (for this the Scripture nowhere acknowledgeth, and beſides, by the ſame reaſon every ſin againſt God would be unpardonable:) but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he that ſinneth againſt the Holy Spirit, doth in the ſame act ſin againſt God (for every ſinne is terminated in God) with an high hand, to wit, either by ſlandering and oppoſing ſuch works, whereof a man is convinced in conſcience that God hath wrought them by his Holy Spirit, as the Phariſees did; or by renouncing and oppoſing ſuch Truths, whereof a man is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced in conſcience that God hath revealed them by his Holy Spirit, as the Renegadoes did, that are mentioned by the Author to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> cha. 10, 25, 26. &amp;c. Which things are the greateſt affronts that can be offered to God, who uſeth the Miniſtry of the Spirit in none but things of the greateſt importance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:114544:13"/>
               <head>An Anſwer to the grand Objection of the Adverſaries touching the ſuppoſed Omnipreſence of the Holy Spirit.</head>
               <p>After I had throughly ſifted this Controverſy, I found that the Adverſaries, who ſo much cry down Reaſon, ſaying that we muſt renounce it when we ſpeak of Divine Myſteries, and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply reſt in the words of the Scripture, do notwithſtanding in the upſhot wave the Scripture, as giving a very uncertain Teſtimony to their Doctrine in this point, and ground themſelves on the mear conjectures of their own Reaſon. For thus they argue, The Holy Spirit, if he were not omnipreſent, and conſequently God, could not inſpire and dwell in ſo many men at one time. For Anſwer hereunto, I will only ask them one queſtion, which if they reſolve, I will then tell them how the Holy Spirit though he be not omni-preſent, may inſpire all the faithfull in the world at one time. Our Saviour in the fourth of <hi>Mark,</hi> explaining the Parable of the ſower, ſaith in verſ. 15. [And theſe are they by the way ſide, where the word is ſown, but when they have heard, Satan commeth immediately and taketh the Word that was ſown in their hearts.] Suppoſe now that the ſeed of the Word be ſown in ten thouſand places at one time, as it hapneth on every Lords day, how can Satan whom the Adverſaries will deny to be omni-preſent, come and immediatly ſnatch the Word out of the hearts of the greateſt part of the Hearers? The ſame reſolution that they ſhall give to this queſtion, will I apply to their own objection. If this bee not ſufficient, take yet more proofs, that may ſeem to evince the omni-preſence of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean ſpirit: Thus is he ſaid to have been a lying ſpirit in the mouth of four hundred falſe Prophets, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 22.22, 23. (and there is the ſame reaſon between four hundred, and foure Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions.) Thus is he ſaid to hold the impenitent (who make the greateſt part of mankinde) in hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſnare, and to take them captive at his will, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. <hi>ult.</hi> To blind the minds of them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve not, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4. To dwell in the ungodly, <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.13. To ſhew the wicked whatſoever they practiſe, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.38. Yea, to deceive the whole world, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.9. &amp; 20.2.3. If they dare not for all this to affirm the uncleane ſpirit to be omni-preſent, why do they on leſſe ground conclude the omni-preſence of the Holy Spirit, eſpecially when the Scripture ſo plainly teſtifyeth that He changeth place, as you may ſee in the eigth Argument above?</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
